A Guide to the S. Michael Polakoff Papers, 1921-2006, Undated
Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
S. Michael Polakoff Papers 1921-2006, Undated
Special Collections, Kegley Library
2013.1
4 folders.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Mary B. Kegley in 2013.
Biographical Information
S. Michael Polakoff, son of Russian immigrants Morris Polakoff and Frances Shafits Polakoff, was born 22 February 1922 in New York City, New York. He served in the United States Navy during World War II and graduated from optometry school in Memphis, Tennessee. In 1949 he moved to Wytheville, Virginia and opened an optometry practice. He married Betty Lou Pattison on 5 December 1959 and lived in the Fulton subdivision of Wytheville. He died on 23 August 2006 in Wytheville.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of four folders: Correspondence (1942, 1944, Undated); Vital Records (1921-2006); Legal Records (1958-1961); and House Construction Records (1960-1970).
Contents List
- Folder 1. Correspondence. 1942, 1944, Undated, 5 items.
  - Letter. Morris Polakoff and Frances Polakoff, New York City, New York to S. Michael Polakoff, Memphis, Tennessee. 14 December 1942., 3 p.; photocopy.
    Re: joining Naval Reserve and trip to New York.
  - Letter. Morris Polakoff, New York City, New York to S. Michael Polakoff. 3 August 1944., 4 p.; photocopy.
    Re: his health, boot camp training, and life in the Navy.
  - Letter. Morris Polakoff, New York City, New York to S. Michael Polakoff. 23 March 194_., 1 p.; photocopy.
    Re: his service in the United States Navy.
  - Letter. Morris Polakoff and Frances Polakoff, New York City, New York to S. Michael Polakoff. Undated., 1 p.; photocopy.
    Re: his friend joining the United States Army.
  - Letter. Frances Polakoff, New York City, New York to S. Michael Polakoff. Undated., 3 p.; photocopy.
    Re: his life in the United States Navy.
- Folder 2. Vital Records. 1921-2006, 7 items.
  - Marriage Certificate. 7 May 1921., 1 p.
    Certificate for Morris Polakoff of Bronx, New York City and Hanna Shafit (Frances) of Bronx, New York City. Hyman Shafit was witness.
  - Certification of Birth. 22 February 1922, 6 February 1946., 1 p.
    Birth certificate of Sol Michael Polakoff, born 22 February 1922, New York City, New York. Certification dated 6 February 1946 from Department of Health.
  - Certificate of Naturalization. 24 April 1928., 1 p.
    Naturalization of Morris Polakoff, native of Russia. Description includes age 32; height 5 feet, 5 inches; dark complexion; brown eyes and hair.
  - Certificate of Naturalization. 10 June 1935, 1 p.
    Naturalization of Fannie Polakoff, native of Russia. Description includes age 40; height 5 feet, 2 inches; fair complexion; blue eyes and brown hair.
  - Certificate of Death. 26 July 1946., 1 p.; photostat.
    Death certificate for Morris Polakoff, died 11 February 1946. Parents were Michael Polakoff and Ida Shaline of Russia; occupation, stationery shop; age 51; burial, Wellwood Cemetery, New York City; cause of death, complications from peptic ulcer surgery; place of death, Fordham Hospital.
  - Certificate of Marriage. 5 December 1959., 1 p.
    Commonwealth of Virginia certificate for marriage of S. Michael Polakoff and Betty Pattison by Rev. J. A. Hardin, Methodist minister, Wytheville, Virginia.
  - Certificate of Marriage. 5 December 1959., 1 p.
    Marriage of S. Michael Polakoff and Betty Pattison by Rev. J. A. Hardin, Methodist minister, Wytheville, Virginia witnessed by Herman L. Jackson Jr., Kathleen P. Jackson, and Mrs. Laurence Pattison.
- Folder 3. Legal Records. 1958-1961., 3 items.
  - Lease Agreement. 12 November 1958., 4 p.
    Lease agreement between Saul Alper, Fannie E. Alper, Gost Fragakis, Helen Fragakis and Dr. S. M. Polakoff for lease of space in the Alper-Hawks Building on Main Street in Wytheville, Virginia.
  - Deed. 1 July 1960., 4 p.
    Deed between Raymond K. Fulton and Thelma W. Fulton of the first part and S. Michael Polakoff and Betty Lou Polakoff of the second part for parcel of land in the Fulton subdivision of Wytheville, Virginia.
  - Deed. 16 January 1961., 4 p.
    Deed between S. Michael Polakoff and Betty Lou Polakoff of the first part and James L. Gleaves Jr. and Willis A. Woods, Trustees, of the second part.
- Folder 4. House Construction Records 1960-1970., 6 items.
  Folder contains documents relating to the construction of a house built by S. Michael Polakoff and Betty Polakoff in the Fulton subdivision in Wytheville, Virginia. Included is an application to build, Description of Materials from Economy Building Company, invoice from Economy Building Company, Deed of Trust Note from Wythe County National Bank for mortgage, invoice from Economy Building Company for extra work on house, and a coupon book recording mortgage payment from S. Michael Polakoff.